all right everyone welcome back to
investing sucks my name is eric and as
always thank you so much for tuning in
so
today we're going to be taking an
in-depth look at some insurance
companies here in canada specifically
we're going to look at the big three
insurance companies so the three largest
in terms of market cap which are
sunlight financial manulife financial
and great west life co so i had a
subscriber mention this idea and i
really liked it i think the idea of
comparing companies is something i
should do more of on this channel
because there are a lot of companies
that are pretty similar and are worth
comparing to each other
and also as you can tell i'm trying out
a new style of video so rather than
using the tv and the camera like i've
been doing in the past
i'm just using screen recording here so
let me know in the comment section if
you like the style of video more and if
you want me to continue to do it if you
think it's better for viewing the
information i'm trying to present to you
just drop a comment and if you guys like
it then i'll continue doing it going
forward so
what we're going to do in this video is
just a quick primer on talking about
things you need to know when looking at
insurance companies from an investment
standpoint so the business model of
insurance some key metrics that you
should look at
why insurance companies are inherently
different than other companies and you
typically value them in non-traditional
ways like you would say with a software
company which we look at a lot of
software companies in this channel as
well
and then we'll take a step back and
review some financial data for each
company so seven years which is what we
always do and then we'll try and value
each one using different valuation
techniques and we're going to keep the
valuation technique super simple and
understandable
um and i think you guys will get a lot
out of doing that and i'll share my
spreadsheet with you guys as well so if
you want to follow along what i'm doing
just go to the description of this video
and hopefully i remember to attach my
spreadsheet there okay so on the screen
i've got kind of what the basic model of
insurance is so this kind of flow chart
here so i've got the insurance business
here
and what i tried to do was show the
different ways that money comes into an
insurance business and it leaves an
insurance business so
obviously there's premiums right that's
what insurance businesses are in the
business of doing now these companies
they're not only insurance companies
they do have wealth management arms too
because they are very large companies
they do a lot
but for the most part they are insurance
so what they do at a very basic level is
they collect premiums from their
customers in exchange for offering them
some type of insurance coverage life
insurance is a big one um for the
companies we're looking at here
and then what they do is they have to
pay their operating costs so they have
to pay their employees rent you know all
their operating talk costs and they also
have to pay
claims payouts when they actually are
required to provide financial coverage
to
uh the people that they've agreed agreed
to insure
and then they invest any excess money
that they either get to keep or that
they have so you'll see something here
that's called float so what float is
is basically a premium money that they
have received but they aren't entitled
to keep yet because they're still liable
for providing insurance coverage because
the term of the insurance contract that
they signed to their customer isn't over
yet so that's what float is but
sometimes they just get to keep the
money
because the customer didn't require the
coverage and the insurance contract
ended so they just get to keep the money
and then they typically invest it and
then they try and earn some type of
return on it
so the value you get in owning an
insurance business
comes in two primary ways one is the
fact that typically not always but
typically they earn more in premiums
than they're required to pay out in
claims
so that's kind of the profitability
aspect and then they also invest the
excess proceeds so they have very large
assets under management or investment
portfolios that they typically invest
rather conservatively with most of it
going into government bonds corporate
bonds uh a lot of it's in cash as well
usually there's a little bit in equity
as well but not as much as
um say you or i would look to if we're
trying to build our own personal
financial portfolios they usually invest
a lot more conservatively
so as you can imagine there's a lot of
internal and external factors that would
impact this for example let's say if
you're a property and casualty insurer
during a time where there's a hurricane
that would not be very profitable right
because there's going to be a lot of
people who are going to require your
insurance coverage and the amount you
have to pay out in claims is probably
going to exceed the amount that you take
in in premiums so it's all about
balancing the risks and rewards that's
really what
insurance companies try to do the best
insurance companies know how or what
types of people or businesses to extend
coverage to that minimizes their risk of
loss but also maximizes their potential
for profitability
so from that we can take a few key
success factors away so one is basically
what i just described which is
effective risk assessments in their
underwriting operations and underwriting
just refers to the act of providing or
deciding who to provide insurance
coverage to
then you also want to see high returns
on the money that they invest
so you don't want to see them making
really bad investments with the money
they keep because if you look at the
balance sheet for a typical insurance
company which we'll do later you'll see
a lot of it is just assets like
investment style assets
and then there's also return on equity
so that's one of the more important
metrics that you're going to see for
insurance companies you usually want to
see this in the range of 12 to 15
percent
sometimes it can be lower
but that's something we're also going to
look at and then down here for a
property and casualty insurer
specifically one
ratio that's pretty common is what's
called the combined ratio so this is
basically you have two aspects of this
the loss ratio and the operating cost
ratio so the loss ratio is kind of your
claims payout so that's the amount of
money that they're kind of earning
that is getting paid into
the claims that they're required to make
so the loss ratio will be higher for a
company that's a property and casualty
insured during a hurricane because they
have to pay out a lot of claims and then
operating costs is just simply refers to
their operating costs so that's one key
metric for property and casualty
insurers specifically but the companies
we're looking at are more life insurers
so something that you've got to kind of
understand about the insurance business
is that it is quite commoditized and
what i mean by that is
there's very little differentiation
between the different shirts if you
think about manulife or sun life and
what the difference is between them
there may be some smaller differences
that you can look at on a more micro
scale but at a high level really what
they do is the same thing there's not a
lot of difference between them so how do
you differentiate between which one is
the better investment becomes a much
more difficult question to answer now
some may contest this point and say well
their customer service could be
different
and they may have insurance contracts
set up with companies that say are
longer term in nature which will benefit
one company more in the long run than
another company that may have
you know shorter term contracts set up
which is definitely true but those types
of things are pretty hard to build into
evaluation
so like i said before you can't really
view valuing a insurance business
through the same lens as you would say
with a software company because with a
software company you can do a discounted
cash flow evaluation because you can
take future scenarios of what their
revenue and what their free cash flow
margins might be
you can very easily discount those back
to the present value and then whatever
your required rate of return is you'll
get a value but it's difficult to do
that with insurance because well for one
they typically don't have any capital
expenditures and the fact that some of
the cash flow that they actually
generate in a given year they may not
actually get to keep because some of it
relates to
premium payments that they receive from
their customers for insurance coverage
that could extend past the current year
so you may see a large cash inflow one
year but that doesn't necessarily mean
that that's cash they get to keep in the
business because later on if a lot of
customers start to make claims they may
have to pay that cash out to them
so you guys know if you've been
following my channel for a while i'm a
big advocate of using
free cash flow when evaluating
businesses as opposed to just looking at
earnings because earnings can be
not manipulated but kind of skewed in
many different ways just depending on
the different things the business is
doing
but in the case of insurance that's not
really what you should be doing and in
my opinion it makes more sense to look
at earnings as opposed to
cash flow so in order to illustrate this
idea i'm going to jump into the
financial statements for sunlight
financial specifically for 2020 so their
most recent annual report and i think
it'll help me illustrate these ideas a
bit better okay so what you're looking
at here is the 2020 annual report for
sunlight financial and specifically
we're looking at their balance sheet or
their statement of financial position
same thing
and you can clearly see that under the
assets section they have a lot of
investment style assets so they've got a
lot of cash on hand which they need they
have debt securities which would be
things like government bonds corporate
bonds they do have some equity
securities which is very small in
relation to the debt securities which
makes sense because they want to invest
more conservatively because a lot of the
a lot of the cash that they have to
invest just comes from the float that we
talked about before and they don't want
to invest their float in equity
securities which could go down a lot in
the short term and then be required to
pay out that money
as a result of a claim coming up so
they're going to invest in more
conservative style assets and they have
quite a lot in mortgages and loans
derivatives which they use to offset
risk and just various types of assets
and if we scroll down to their
liabilities section we can see that by
far their biggest liability is this
insurance contract liability so all this
is is just an estimate
of the future amount of money that they
will need to pay out to their insur to
the people they're insuring basically
so it's an estimate so it's not going to
be 100 accurate but for a company like
sun life they're insuring so many
different people i mean literally
millions of people
you can assume it'll be ballpark what
this is so nothing really to worry about
there unless there's some drastic event
that completely changes the world then
this number should be about accurate so
based on that you can kind of understand
why looking at book values specifically
which book value also just means equity
so there's total equity here which is
just
total assets minus total liabilities you
can understand why that's such an
important metric for when you're
evaluating insurance companies you can
usually tell that a lot of people when
they're looking at insurance companies
they'll talk about price to book value
so the company's current market
capitalization in relation to that book
value and the reason that's the case is
because book value is basically just the
excess value that the business currently
has
if you assume that they sell off all
their investment style assets and then
settle all their outstanding claims so
it's kind of like the liquidation value
of the business now as a general rule
you'll usually see insurance companies
valued somewhere between one and two
times their book value now that can
change a lot going under one times your
book value is pretty rare and you
usually only see that with companies
during recessionary times although it
does happen occasionally
okay and then if we scroll up we get to
the statement here which is consolidated
statement of operation so basically
their income statement
and this is going to help highlight why
i think earnings is very important to
look at so in the revenue obviously a
lot of the revenue just comes from
premiums that they receive so that's
this number here but also a lot of it
comes from investment income so that's
the two types of revenue remember when i
showed you that flow chart about you
know just the business model of
insurance you had your premiums then you
also had your investment income so their
investment income will be
partly here which is their interest
and then there's also fair value changes
so they make investments in debt
securities equity securities and they
have to constantly revalue those assets
and make sure they're on their financial
statements at their current fair value
so if they increase in value that gets
shown up in their revenue section here
which would be
fair value changes here so it's not
really necessarily a cash inflow to them
because it's really just an increase in
the value of those assets that they hold
but it is a significant part of what
you're getting when you invest in
insurance business i mean normally for
companies i would say don't look at that
as much but because the investment
portfolios or the general fund as it's
usually called for these insurance
businesses is so important it's such a
big part of what you're getting when you
invest in their common stock you
definitely need to look at it
and then if we just scroll down look at
some of the expenses obviously they've
got their operating expenses down here
which would be their you know wages to
employees that type of stuff and then
they've got some changes in liability so
there's the increase or decrease in
insurance contract liabilities so
they've signed new insurance contracts
obviously during the year that they earn
those premiums on and they're also
required to record an estimate of the
future obligation that they have
relating to those to the insurance
coverage they're providing so this
number represents an increase in that
obligation which obviously that
obligation would increase because
they're signing new contracts and
they're going to have they're going to
be required to pay out the claims to
some of those contracts so that's what
that number represents there
and then there's also this one here
which is the claims that they actually
had to pay out during the year
okay so now that you've got a good idea
of the business model of insurance and
how to actually evaluate insurance
companies from an investment standpoint
let's dig into the financial history of
these three companies so we'll start
with sun life we're going to look at the
two different ways of valuing them which
i talked to it before which is the book
value method and the earnings method so
let's look at some information that's
relevant to that
so with sun life we have seven years of
information on their assets their
liabilities now i've also included
preferred shares information because
what we want to do in the book value
method here specifically is calculate
book value per share now when we're
doing that we're calculating book value
per common share so because there's
preferred shares that these companies
have we have to make sure we take that
out of the book value calculation so
that's all this number is here just
assets minus liabilities minus preferred
shares super simple
so we can see over the past seven years
their book value has grown at about five
point three percent a year
and then they're also buying back shares
so their shares went from 611 million
down to 585 so that's a good sign to see
they're giving you more ownership in
their company
and then their price to book value an
average over the last seven years was
1.46 which you know that's that's
slightly high i mean we can compare it
to the other companies when we get to
there but the lowest it was ever at was
in 2018 which was
1.22 so that is historically if we look
at where it's been that's pretty low so
we can tell from that metric alone that
2018 was probably a good time to buy sun
lifestock and clearly because the share
price and that time was about 45 dollars
and it's since climbed to near 60
dollars so
uh that's one metric that can give you a
lot of information about when is a good
time to get in on an insurance company
when they're representing good value
is when the price to book value ratio is
historically low and i think the only
reason it was low in 2018 was because
2018 in general was a pretty bad year
for
just the market as a whole i think uh if
you go back before the
since the 2008 financial crisis 2018 was
the worst
year now if we move over here to the
earnings method we can see
their revenue has grown historically at
about 7.7 percent their earnings at
about four and a half percent again we
have shares here so their earnings per
share the earnings per share is actually
growing at a faster rate than their
earnings itself and the only reason for
that is just because they're buying back
shares so that's definitely a good sign
to see and then i have this number here
called earnings yield so all earnings
yield is
is it's basically just a reverse price
to earnings ratio so like an earnings to
price ratio so if you had an earnings
yield of five percent that would be a 20
pe
so it's been rather stagnant i mean
hasn't really moved that much you can
see the higher the earnings yield that
means you're getting the better value so
again 2018 was the time to get in really
but it's averaged about seven and a half
percent so that's sun life financial now
let's move down to manulife here
and see how they compare so let's move
straight down since we already explained
how the assets and the book values
calculated
book value has been growing at seven
point or six point seven percent
historically so a bit faster than sun
life but not really that much
and their price to book value is quite
significantly lower i mean let's see
where it's been historically it's
noticeably
under the value of sun life sun life was
1.46 manual life is 1.11 so that begs
the question
why is that well if we move over we look
at the earnings method here it's going
to provide us some information on this
so we can see if we look at their
revenue
it's been rather it hasn't been very
stagnant throughout the years and in
fact it's fluctuated quite a lot we can
see here about 54 billion then down to
34 billion then back to about where it
was before and then it went down again
and then in recent years it's gone up a
lot so when i saw that initially i was
kind of thought to myself well they're
probably you know investing in companies
or maybe they divested a current
business but that's actually not the
case the reason that it's fluctuating so
much is because of just the way they
have their portfolio set up
so the revenue drop in 2014 to 2015 was
largely due to
a decrease in the value of their oil and
gas investments remember before i showed
you guys on the income statement one of
the key items in the revenue side of
their income statement is the change in
the value of the of their investment
portfolio as a whole they have to adjust
it to fair value so if it increases
that's represents more revenue but if it
loses value that represents
a lot less revenue so that's basically
what's happening here
and then like i said in 2018 2018 was
generally a pretty dismal year for you
know investments as a whole so that's
why it went down so much and then the
past few years
has been pretty good for equities so
it's gone up quite a lot but overall the
revenue has grown 5.4 with earnings
growing at 7.77 so earnings are growing
faster
than sun life you know that's that's the
fact no one can really argue with that
but they are
issuing additional shares not by much
only 0.4 a year but it still is there
so their earnings per share is actually
growing slower
than their earnings just because they're
issuing more shares and then the
earnings yield
has averaged about eight eight percent
which is a bit higher than sun life
which means investors genuinely value
sun life a bit more than manulife and
the reason for that and also probably
the reason for their price to book value
being so much lower 1.11 versus 1.46 is
just because of this fluctuation you see
here
because clearly they aren't really
hedging their investments
as well as say sun life because sunlight
isn't fluctuating nearly as much there
is definitely some fluctuation pretty
much in line with what you see with
manulife
but it's a lot less extreme so that's
probably just investors compensating for
that additional risk that's probably
part of it maybe there's some other
reason why
sun life is valued slightly higher than
manulife if we look at it from the book
value perspective but just seeing that
alone it tells me there's probably some
they're compensating themselves for some
additional risk that they see in
manulife
now let's move down and look at the last
one which is great west life go
so great west life co is kind of in the
middle it's not as big as manual life
but it's bigger than say sun life is
so let's look at their book value so
it's been growing 3.2 so that's a lot
lower than the other ones we looked at
but their shares outstanding they've
been buying back shares a lot more
actively decreasing at over one percent
a year and their price to book value is
1.42 so
actually it's lower than sun life but a
lot higher than what you see with
manulife so
and then based on that
we're probably going to see a lot less
fluctuation in their revenue again for
that same reason i described maybe
they're doing better with the way they
hedge their investments so they're not
as subject to fluctuate as much with the
market which is clearly the case i mean
we don't see any huge fluctuations but
there are definitely some
but overall revenue has been growing six
percent a year earnings two percent
and then earnings per share three
percent again that's just because
um of they're buying back a lot more
shares and their earnings yield is eight
point three two percent so
the best value we're gonna see is a high
earnings yield but a low price to book
ratio
so from that alone we'd probably
conclude that sun life presents the best
value because
their earnings yield is the highest and
their price to book value is the lowest
i mean the earnings yield is 8.35 here
which is pretty similar to that 8.32 we
see here with great west
um but just based on that alone you'd
say you know manulife is looking pretty
good but obviously past what the past is
doesn't always indicate what the future
will hold
um so we're going to dig into that a bit
more but one thing i want to show you
guys
further
is their portfolio so i've taken
snippets of their financial reports so
we can look at how their portfolios are
actually broken down so this is sun
life's their investment portfolio
so and this is what they call their
general fund which is basically just you
know this is assets that they own they
don't hold it in trust for anyone else
it's assets that they own themselves
so most of it is in debt securities 48
and then a lot of it's in mortgages they
only have four percent in equities so
you know that's pretty standard like i
said before these companies invest
rather conservatively
now if we move down to manulife you can
see the percentage of total is here
so they presented it a bit differently
but we can see
it's it's not really that much different
i mean they got six percent in equities
which is higher
which those typically fluctuate more
than you would say with bonds but one
thing you've got to note about all these
companies is that they are
at risk if interest rates rise because
as we know interest rates if they rise
they move in the opposite direction as
some of the government bonds and because
these companies have to report the value
of their investments at the fair value
and record the increases or decreases on
the income statement like i showed
if interest rates rise the value of
these bonds that they hold will decrease
so they are vulnerable to interest rates
rising now it's not really going to hurt
their businesses that much but it is
going to result in lower revenue and
probably lower earnings as well
so let's move down to great west here
and see how they differ
and again really not much difference i
mean
six percent in stocks they got 14 in
mortgages which is a bit lower a lot
more in
uh bonds so government bonds and
corporate bonds in the other two but
really nothing to write home about i
mean no huge difference in the
investment portfolio but this is
definitely something you want to look at
for any insurance company because this
is really going to tell you how they're
investing the money because when you
invest in the common shares of any
insurance business what you're getting
is of course a piece of their future
earnings but also their investment
portfolio which you need to know that is
and they outline it here now one last
thing i want to talk about before we
move on is these companies return on
equity so return on equity is a very
important metric to look at with
insurance businesses and we can clearly
see that manual life has the lowest of
the two sun life at about 11.2 great
west 11 and a half and manual life only
about 8.9 percent
if we take an average of the last seven
years so perhaps that might be another
reason why investors are discounting
manulife stock a little bit compared to
sun life in great west just because they
don't have as great a historical track
record as
generating returns on the equity
invested in the business
okay so now let's actually jump into the
valuations of these companies so i've
done two valuation methods for each
company now these valuation methods are
super simple and again i'm going to
attach my spreadsheet
in the description of this video so if
you guys want to look at the arithmetic
i use to determine all this stuff then
you'll be able to do that but i did it
for the next seven years for each one
so one is the book value method so this
method is really simple all i'm doing is
so we're taking sun life here is i'm
just assuming that their book value is
going to grow at the exact same rate
it's been growing yet in the past seven
years that we looked at i assume that
their price to book value is going to
stay the average of what it was in the
past seven years they're going to
continue to buy back shares at the exact
same rate
and then we basically see what type of a
return do we get based on that
so their book values here it grows at
5.37 percent a year
their price to book value is represented
by this number now one thing i will say
is currently based on their current
share price which as i'm recording this
is 68.3 dollars
their price to book value based on that
is 1.67 which is actually quite high i
mean we saw
or we saw it was historically it's been
about 1.46 so from a historical
perspective it is quite expensive now
which naturally is going to mean if
we're valuing it in the future based on
a 1.46 book value ratio the returns will
be pretty low so only 3.86 here but
this method you should really just use
as a way of identifying how expensive
the company is currently
in relation to how it's been in the past
from a book value perspective because
this doesn't take into account dividends
which dividends are a huge part of how
you get or how you make your money on
investing an insurance company and all
these insurance companies from what i
understand pay pretty solid dividends
so the better method to use i think is
the earnings method now the arithmetic
is pretty similar we just take the
earnings we assume the earnings grow
at the exact same rate they've been
growing in the past so we're applying a
uniform growth percentage
um just you know take all emotion out of
it take all
just keep it super objective
we're assuming the earnings yield will
just stay exactly what it's been in the
past so then we get a market cap and we
see the market caps growing just at the
exact same rate of their earnings
they continue to buy back shares at the
exact same rate and then here's our
price per share
so based on that if we put this into an
irr calculator where we get our so we
buy the shares at the current price and
then we'd basically assume they get that
stream of earnings which that earnings
can be
you know distributed out in the form of
dividends and then the terminal value
here so we get a
irr of 7 which again isn't that high
we're usually looking for about 10 15
irr when it comes to investing in
individual companies
but an insurance company is naturally
going to probably produce a lower irr
especially now
because we've been in such a low
interest rate environment for so long
that the value of these companies as we
could clearly see
is going to be bid up a little bit which
we can see that evidenced in the price
to book value ratio 1.67
versus 1.46 being the average for the
last seven years
okay now let's see how this compares to
manulife so we're going to do the exact
same thing for all the companies just
apply the exact same methodology where
we just take historical results project
them into the future again the reason we
do this is just to get a completely
unbiased perspective
on what type of returns these companies
could offer this isn't my crystal ball
projection of what i think the future
will hold for all these companies
because that's going to depend a lot on
the economy and really just what's going
on in the world as a whole
but it does help us put their current
valuations into perspective okay so now
we're moving on to manulife and as we
saw before
their price to book value historically
for last seven years 1.11 was a lot
lower than the other companies which was
in the 1.4 range and currently their
price to book value is actually below
one it's 0.98
so
from that information alone you would
say well now would be a good time to get
into manual life financial but we don't
want to just look at one data point we
want to look at context as a whole
so if we use the book value method we
apply the exact same methodology that we
did with sun life so book value grows
at 6.7 which it had grown historically
in the last seven years
shares go up slightly because we saw
they weren't actually buying back shares
they're increasing their shares that
gives us a return of 8.3 so that's much
higher than we saw with sun life
now let's look at the earnings method
because like i said the earnings method
i like to use more because it takes into
account dividends and obviously you want
to account for dividends that's a big
part of how you get your money back in
these investments
so earnings of 6.1 billion in 2021 is
what we're assuming
and again that's just taking what they
were last year and then applying the
growth rate which is the same growth
rate had been in the past so seven point
seven seven percent
and then the earnings yield is how it
was before and then we get or basically
what it's been in the last seven years
so eight point three five percent
and we can see our market cap grows and
it gets to about 115 billion market cap
we divide that by
1 billion 995 million shares outstanding
we get a price per share of 57.78 and
then if we put all that into an irr
calculator
our irr is quite high we get an
estimated 20 return now
i do think that applying this method to
menu life is it does kind of give off a
little the results are a little skewed
and the reason i say that is because if
we go to their
financials here
we can see we can look at their earnings
and yes they've grown seven point seven
seven percent a year but they were quite
high in the past two years
and that's really because manulife just
has a more risk attitude towards
managing their portfolio as we can
clearly see with the fluctuations so
when times are good manual life is going
to do a lot better than great west life
co and sun life but when times are bad
and the value of their investment is
falling they're not going to do quite as
good so i do think that this valuation
here is a little bit skewed and i think
20 ir is a bit too high to anticipate
but you can't deny that manulife
comparatively offers pretty good value
now let's just conclude and look at
great west life co here see how they
stack up again they're kind of in the
middle so if we use the book value
method we're getting 3.7
um
and their current price to book value
pretty much on par with what it's been
in the last seven years so all we're
really assuming here is that
um
the return is basically just gonna be in
line with the growth in their book value
which was three point three percent in
the last seven years so let's focus more
on the earnings method
so again we just assumed their earnings
is growing at what had been historically
which was
relatively low compared to the other
companies 2.07 percent
and then they have the same earnings
yield that they had in the last seven
years
so here's our market cap and we can see
how this kind of grows to about about 41
billion in 2027.
um we assume that they continue to buy
back shares at 1 and then we get a price
per share of 47.2 in the year 2027. so
our compensation for investing them will
consist of all the dividends we receive
plus you know the earnings which they
can pay out in dividends or they can
just retain it in the business
so we get an ir of nine percent so again
kind of in the middle
so great west life go offering 9 i think
that is pretty solid i think all of
these companies are generally low risk
investments and we have highlighted some
differences in between them
and you know with manulife offering 20
irr don't take that necessarily as i
should jump on this company right now
just because i think
the numbers are skewed but what it does
highlight is that manual life has
generally they accept risk more
than great west life co and sun life so
that's definitely something to consider
okay so now i'm just going to offer some
concluding thoughts here so
based on the very you know financial
type analysis that we just did i would
definitely put manual life as number one
great west life goes number two and sun
life is number three now does that
necessarily mean that
the companies are going to have you know
are going to perform in that exact order
that i just listed no not necessarily
and really when it comes to insurance
companies you're investing in their
future earnings right not just what
their historical earnings have been but
what their earnings are going to be
going into the future and what you need
to focus on is something called premium
growth potential so i put that here in
this section here
and what that really relates to is how
they're offering new insurance products
or they're expanding into different
markets and they're successfully
expanding into those new markets so
the life insurance market in china
this is just super basic research i did
it's grown about 12
compounded annually
from 2009 to 2019. so it'd be best to
examine how each company is performing
in china and other emerging economies
because that's going to show
can they actually grow their premiums
which would result in them being able to
contribute more into their investment
funds grow the value of the business
overall that's one of the most important
things
and then like i said one of the reasons
that manulife could be trading at lower
multiples historically doesn't
necessarily mean that
it's just cheap and investors are just
asleep at the wheel and they're not
recognizing value that's right in front
of them it just probably means they're
not mitigating as much risk
and it's likely that interest rates will
rise in the future which like i said
before would negatively impact
pretty much all of manulife's investment
portfolio as well as the other ones but
more so manulife just because
as we've seen from the historical
financials here
they just fluctuate a lot more than the
other companies so if you're willing to
accept a bit more risk then you could
probably go with manulife but if you
want a little bit less risk you don't
want to see as much fluctuation in the
revenue the earnings then probably look
at great west or sun life that's kind of
my conclusion okay so that was a lot
but uh thank you so much for listening
guys i hope you got a lot out of this
and i hope you learned something if you
are new to my channel i greatly
appreciate if you consider subscribing i
do these types of videos pretty much
weekly and with that in mind see in the
next video